All right everybody thank you for coming out
today had a request if you're sitting in a row if you could screwed into the middle with still
...people coming in we don't have enough chairs if you can just
...room I'm sure people would appreciate that.
My name is ron miller I work as a program manager on the entity framework
team at microsoft the topic of our session today is entity framework seven.
So, I just wanted to set expectations about the session before we start
out first of all this is listed as a level two hundred session
so that means first of all it's not a one-oh-one introduction to entity framework if you haven't used
...before hopefully you'll still get a bit of information out of the session
bad it's not going to be an introduction the...it's probably going to make more sense to you if you use the
...or at least satin sessions on entity framework before on the flip side of that it's also not
level four hundred session it's not a deep dive we are going to spend most of the time
encode but we're not going to be digging into the super technical bits of...seven.
This may seem obvious but this is a session about aef seven which is in preview at the moment so
this is afford look at what's coming out in entity framework in the future it's not a look at
...current stable releases if you want info
unstable releases there's lots of sessions and videos and documentation online that you can take a
look at and I've got some links for-you at the end where you can head for stuff like that.
Our agenda is very simple we're going to spend a couple of minutes in slide's talking about what you
have seven is if you've been an if seven session before you've probably seen this
content done stress...on a couple of minutes and I'm going to dig into demos most of the demos
I'm doing and you things I haven't shown before and then at the end we'll wrap up with
some places you can head to if you want to learn more about aef seven or get involved in the project.
So, the tag line we've been using for...seven is new platforms and you data
stores which sounds great on this slide but let's talk about what that actually means.
So, in...new platform side historically af ran on the
full dot net framework that meant you could use it in places such as wpf when
forms consul applications and isp dot net.
If you have seven way opening up a whole bunch of different platforms this is the same
messaging been hearing from a whole bunch of teams at this conference we add to use...on
...net five now...at five targets the full dot net framework but
it also targets net core...seven...in both of those scenarios.
Because we target dot net call you'll be out use...seven against dot net core on
windows ten universal application platform on mac and linux
...course mono is also available mac and linux so you can use...seven tagging that as well the point of
this slide is...that you can use entity framework...you would be writing dot net
code now of course not every provider is going to work in every situation so
the specific providers that are available what differ depending on what platform...targeting.
The other part about tag on
data stores historically af has just been about targeting relational data
...seven way opening it up to also target non relational data stores now
...very clear this is not about building some kind
of magical framework that hides the type of data store using
because things demo great and I never work and real applications so our aim is to take
the common concerns that makes sense on all data stores like having a db
context that represents a session with the data store tracking the changes and then handing those to the data
...of assist the concept of having a link query
provided that is handed off to the data store to translate into native query syntax
that stuff we baked into the core and then other stuff that does not apply to all data
stores comes in is a set of extensions when you pick the provide
audio targeting so the example I normally use for this
...targeting something non relational like as a table storage I need to do things like
configuring the...partition...for each entity that would be
an extension method that comes in one ice target...a table storage if on targeting
...database than I care about things like configuring cascade delete and
cullen table mappings...come in as extension methods when I target any relational provider.
And, just to give you some examples of what we've been working on our team has been working on
sequel severance...light providers and we've also been working with the mpg sequel
...some post grass.
And, then there's a whole bunch of other people who are in the earlier stages of looking at provide
...seven as well in addition...team has been prototyping as a table storage and
...providers these are included in a current...releases
we've just been prototyping them so...ready to ship them yet but we are planning to ship them further down the road.
And, then we've also...in memory database ...provide...the point of this is not to use
in a production application but if you have a part of your application that you want to test against
entity framework...you want your tests to run quickly rather hitting a database all the time you can
flickr out for the in memory provide a and well-behaved for the most part like a relational provide a
...you to easily test against entity framework obviously that's not going to be
what might they would do for a tree unit testing where you want to hone in on one piece of code
and test that but it would be useful if you want to do something that's a bit more like a scenario test of
...nbc control or something actually see it hit entity framework can get data back.
So, in addition to new platforms new data stores have seven we're
...opportunity to kind of re-invent or
...the core of entity framework so we want to make the core components that
...builds over much more lightweight and extensible.
...of the clear the top-level experience is still entity framework you stole
derived from a db context you expose db sets you have the same top-level api is that
you're used to entity framework under the covers though when we talk about the
core we're talking about things such as the metadata system the object model that
actually keeps track of what your entities look like how they mapped to your data structure
...data store and all those things we're talking about the internal components that
keep track of changes to objects as you manipulate them in memory
we're talking about the under the covers pipeline that translates your link query into something
that...be translated into store specific query syntax.
So, even though things like change tracking...on the list.
Which changing the core components...but the api from db context
like db context dot change tracker the api still looks almost identical to what it did in
...releases even though we're changing metadata the fluent api for configuring
your model still looks almost identical to what...releases as well?
So, why redo the core some of the main reasons obviously because it's extensible
you can replace...extend the components now this could be something you do it also makes it
easier for third-party frameworks to hook into entity framework and
add additional value an example of this being glimpse which is
logging in diagnostics plug-in for sp net they had a really hard time plugging into
fsix and with the architecture we have any of seven...life a lot easier for them
which will hopefully help out ecosystem with better tools and plugins available?
Was also an opportunity to replace confusing...and behavior
...ip...didn't make any sense I don't know if anyone in the rooms ever used a metadata api
from previous releases of...if you have I'm sorry but in the have seven
with making it so it's actually looks like an api that maps
...classes to a data store.
Ef six core was built in a very monolithic fashion the code
vices about twenty-years-old so with squeezed...much better perf out of the
later releases of entity framework but...wasn't a whole lot...we can go with a...this call that
we're building is optimized for memory and cpu usage and
this is particular important as we move to cloud computing and devices on devices
resources on super abundant in the cloud we pay for the resources we use so let's see
the you can actually main less billing at the end of the month which is good for you.
And, then another another concept we tried to embraces we built this is paper plight so if you
use entity framework to target something that's not a relational database relational
parts of the stack...separated out into a separate assembly by one get installed into a projects
...loaded up into memory when you run your application you just pay for the bits of...that you actually use.
And, of course you call means we can also implements and features that were incredibly difficult first
implement on the old core so this is just a list of some of the things that a new and
...seven folks have been asking for a long-time.
Some highlights of the list so batching...of commands during...changes we
...one command to the database for every row that you change allowing
...to be evaluated in memory and some of the other things on the list that too.
All right so I promise the slide section was going to be shorten that's it I'm going to drop out and start looking
at some demos now before we actually start digging around
in the new features I just want to introduce you to the organization we're going to be
...of following along for the series of demos I have.
the company...working for is code unicorns store these guys are an online retailer
they have this public-facing store where you can shop around as you might
expect unicorns store allows you to purchase everything that has pictures of cute little unicorns on it.
Ef has a history with unicorns which if you want to know about you can come up and I'll
explain to you at the end all right so this public-facing website is implemented using sp
dot net five so let's...studio and we have an sp dot net five
application if we look at the references for this when you get packages we'll see that.
We have
...the installed ones so we have entity framework dot sequel server installed so this is
the sequel server provider because...application...working with
target sequel server now this is actually important point because historically the sequel server
provide was actually built into the core of entity framework so we install the entity framework package even if you
are going to target oracle you still had the sequel server assembly there was
loaded into memory now it's split out...sequel...really just another provider.
So, let's look at the models we have we actually have to models here...bit here so we have the
...dot net identity model so this is the default model that is there when you
...application it manages the logins for this application I've actually also extended
that to include things like addresses for the uses and,
some other information like that and thena little further down we have the actual unicorns
store model here and this represents the product catalog the categories that
the products belong to when people can put stuff in that
cots and place orders and the shipping details for the orders and everything like that.
Now just to prove that any framework still looks the same any of seven if we light up one about
...classes that looks exactly like what we expect just a simple
...class.
Has properties with get doesn't settles on it?
And, then if we look at context say that
we still inheriting from db context were still exposing a db set for each
type and model and we're still overriding on model creating to provide
some additional configuration based on what was discovered by convention.
I play that gives you a brief intro to.
The...be working with what start digging into some features
of ewf so the first thing I want to do is look at logging in entity framework seven it's
probably not the most exciting demo to start with but I want to show you some of the
sequel improvements that we've made in the best way to do that is to
start by implementing logging so we can actually see what's happening in the database.
So, I was...back to visual studio I've made a start on the logging code I have the sequel
logo the intent of this component is to log any interaction with the database so I want to
find any sequel statements being executed...them out to a file you can see...I
...now one important thing I...not an entity framework specific type this comes
from the microsoft framework dot logging package and its use by entity framework
its used by sp dot net five and all of its components and hopefully used by
...frameworks in the future too.
The core of the log interfaces the log method.
Now in the past in a log method you might have expected just to get a string to log.
Out log here is actually a bit better than that we have the ability to...state so this gives
...called structured logging so if I'm about to send a command to the database I don't just have to send you
a string with the sequel in it I can actually give you the db command and then your
...can do something intelligent based on what's passed in now rather giving the db command would probably
actually just give you a detail object with some of the information copied out of the command
cannot really wanna-be manipulating stuff from the logging framework but you get the idea
are not just getting strings I can actually get real information but in some cases
like my scenario actually do just want to string so the last parameter we give you as a...
which takes all the information I just talked about and turns it into a human readable string.
I should also mention the exception comes in here so another example of what I
can do if I could check and see if the exceptions not now and maybe it's a
sequel exception I can run some extra logic to log the fact that a
sequel exception happened and I can actually gets the properties that are specific to a
sequel exception we don't want to do that I...going to run the formatted to get the message
musing a string...format to turn it into something a little more pretty and then we're just going to go on
write that out to a file in my see temp directory called database dialogue.
Now logging doesn't stop with the
...is actually one more level above that there's what's called a logging provider so
if I open this...happens is that every component in entity framework and I
mention that entity frameworks much more modular now every component asks the
...for the logarithm should use so this gives me the opportunity to give a different
...each component so in my case I'm only interested in giving the sequel
...to components that actually going to produce
equal so I've got a list where I've store the names of lies the batch
...the query context factory the two things that produce equal any of seven so I'm going to check
give the component requesting this belongs in that list.
So, the name of the components requesting a logo and if it is I'm going to return.
One about...logan's.
Like and if it's not I'm just going to return a now logo and this is just something that's not going...do anything...logs no way.
All right so I could go ahead and register this logging stuff directly with entity framework but I'm working
and isp dot net five application and isp dot net five has a concept of dependency injection bike
...into it so instead of registering my provided directly with...many
...startup well all my services setup we just go down a bit we'll see.
That my db contexts...being registered with the dependency injection
container now this is important means if I have a controller that needs to use one of the
context of new adopt in the controller I can just ask the dependency injection
...for the context it...give it to me the other thing that's important with this
...also means a context can make use of any services from the
...so I'm going to register my logo with the di container and then all of that would take care of
...that into entity framework now of course evolves running in
a wpf application I didn't want to use dependency injection and have to do it this way if I
don't use adi contain af we'll just take care of viewing up the services that needs?
So, we...down a little further and.
Come down to where actually setting up the loggers so we're going to add a provider.
Finish this been a...obvious because I think of lost intelligence so will...now...
there ...run application nouns what happens so you notice I can register multiple provided so if I
run this application from the command-line then I would get I would get
output from the log streaming straight out to the consul but I also have my
sql log in register to so let's just browser store.
And, great everything's
reworking and...just going to open up that log and
...the language the sql because that would give us a nice syntax highlighting and.
Zoom if you guys because...the screens not great so you can see that
we're now getting all of the sequel statements odf is running logged out to this file.
...just give me a sector close-ups and then I'll...back to the...
So, if we get our intelligence back.
All right well that's three loading let's go back over here.
Right so the next demo we're going to look at is some of the
sequel generation improvements we've done so we want to look at some improvements we've made in the save changes pipeline.
Get...online to...on a to...back into the application.
All right so let's just run our app.
And, I want to show you a part of the application that I'll get when I login.
All...so I'm going to login.
All right so the credentials I just log in with happen to be an administrator in the unicorns store so I get
this section of the application where I can do things like managing the products and the other thing I can do here is a
bulk process update so I can pick a category in-store let's
say kitchen and dining and I can say we want to give like a twenty five percent discount across all products
and the application of press save and we'll see at the
moment doesn't do anything we can see listed on the screen here that the current
process is still the same...up at the moment so let's go ahead and implement
this functionality...back to visual studio.
And, going to go into my control is an open up the manage products...so this is a
control that drives that admin section that I was just looking at we have an action on here
cobalt price reduction you can say we're going ahead with loading up all the products from
the database that in the category that was selected calculating the discount within the to go
...apply...so I'm going to say product current price and we're
...to set that to the recommended retail price.
So, we're going to...through all the products and do that and once we finish setting that for all the product...go ahead and call save changes?
...run the application.
...price reduction I'm going to pick on kitchen and
...again let's give a bigger discount let's make everything half-price.
Hit save...worked this time now in entity framework six what
would've happened is I would've changed the current price always for products I would've
called save and we would have sent for round trips to the database what we'll see if we go back to our log.
Is if I zoom in for
...probably have a guy will see that everything is kind of patched up into a single round-trip
to the database now you might be looking at this with an update and saying well that's great
you just always append all the actions together and if I do for inserts my just going to
say like insert into blah insight into blah...not
actually quite smart and how we build the batch so if I was inserting ten products I would
...insert into product columns I'm going to insight into and then I
...just say for value line underneath that list the values to...we also have a lot of smarts and
...obviously do topological sought to make sure that the parent objects get instead
of before children and in some situations where we need to we break it up into separate batches as
well that could be based on either the need to get values from the database before we can insert
...child records or even just the batch
sizes an optimal batch size to run for different database providers?
Now that's a feature that people have been asking for a long-time
on entity framework six it would've been very expensive for us to do their but it was easy for us to
...can from the start with a much more extensible core.
All right so the next mi want to show you is actually
...sequel improvement as well and that's when I run role sql queries against the database.
So,...what back to visual studio.
...application and I'm going to search by here or search box on the top
I might want to search for shirts.
If I search for show
...get any results back of the moment so let's go look at the action driving this.
That would be on the shop...an action...search.
We'll say the moment we're not actually returning anything from the results.
So, from my db context...could look at the products db set and then I
could write a link query here I could say where the title contains the term
or the description contains a term or it has a picture with the tag
or caption that mentions the term...probably not going to be the most efficient to do it I probably want to use
something like full-text search or some other database optimized feature to do
the search and that's actually exactly what I've got if we go to server explorer.
And, we look at the database...targeting.
You see I have a table valued function here it
accepts the search term and then the result set is just the columns out of the product table.
Now entity framework doesn't have the native building ability at this stage to call it tv
p so instead of using link I'm going to use this from sequel method
...a similar to what we had any fsix I would just punch in some sequel here.
Or call out tv...we need to
...a parameter now I'm not going to do string concatenation here because that would make me...the sequence
action tax so many...a parameter and then we make things nice
...you can just...the actual value and we'll take care of wrapping it up in a...parameter
for you so run this and this is an earth-shattering you could whoops.
I...just make sure the basic functionality as work and then we'll take a step further so I should be able
to search for shirt now and I can in the shirts come back okay.
Now what's interesting is the stuff is just coming back and whatever order it came from the database
...tv pay doesn't do any sorting in it so maybe I want to display
...the cheapest items first because I know in the context of the store
...the items that people in most likely to...
Now I could go to sequel and I could say okay or by but I'm using
rm for reason I don't really want to be writing...all the time.
So,...be nice if I could just dot composing on top of this using link.
Like that now this is across strongly taught divide change the names of the properties
avoiding all the pitfalls that would come with writing sequel let's run this.
Search for
shuts again and we'll see that now they order let's go look at the sequence running.
Zooming here you'll see the piece of sequel that I specified in the middle there and
then because it's something that's...were able to rapid an add extra sequel around it so
way selecting out the cones we expect and ordering by the current price.
All right so the last thing that I wanted to show you.
With something code what's on the last...stress the last bit of this
...demos want to show you something called shadow state...
...six if you want something to be part of your model what had to...class.
And, had to have properties everything that you...model the concept
of shadow state is the ability to have stuffing a model that's not actually represented in you'll see a
...classes now this can be useful in a number of different scenarios that may be that the
classic using is your...something un comes from a library that's just an
assembly you therefore can't add stuff to it.
Or it could be that stuff that you want to kind of reason about with the...we don't really want to
...you see a lot classes that the rest of your application is built over.
So, we're actually looking at one that second scenario what we
want to do is add some information to the
cops items that people can add so when I'm shopping around
...item to my cot we want to track the time that each
...item was last updated now the reason we want to do that is...just been sitting in somebody's
cot for year haven't touched we want to both...it out of
the cut because chances are...don't want to if I come back to the...and also we just want to free up the space
...the database now what I would traditionally do here.
Obviously is...my model.
I would light up the...class and I would add a property
code last updated...really want to do that though because I don't want
developers exposing it somewhere in the ui so instead I'm going to go to my context.
We're going to pull out the configuration for the...item.
...to...dot property now this is traditionally where I would have put in some lambda,
lambda that says which property on my cdl-class want to talk about instead I'm going to use and
overlaid where specified type.
...last updated and then at this point I could chain on some additional configuration
to do things like setting the column that should map to in the database same as...accessing
...allow property from the class I'm happy with all the defaults...leave it like that for the moment.
Now in this case I'm using a
seven to create and maintain the database for me so this is
...what this is where I write code and then I have the database generated make changes to the code and I push
...changes to the database and of course the scenario can do things like getting a sequel script to
...my db a and production I just want to call it out because sometimes when we demo
this workflow people are under the impression that that's kind of the recommended way of using entity framework
is one of the to options you can use ef to create your model and then
...update your database from it or it's also equally valid and equally important
of a scenario to have an existing database that you generate a model from so that's just a point of clarification?
Anyway,
like I said at this point my model is a source of truth and I want to push these changes to my database so
I would use code first migrations for that now what I would be used to doing here is
I would go ahead and run something like ad migration from package manager consul.
But, I'm in the context of...dot net five.
So, I...on...five also have the concept of
building commands so...I go and look at project jason file you'll see that I have a reference to the entity
framework dot commands package.
And, then in my command section I have...ef command registered.
So, that gives me another option of dropping out to the command prompt.
And, I can do dn x which is kind of the entry point when I'm working with isp dot net five and I can say I want to called
...command.
So, this gives me a consul alternative for the commands related to
...now at the moment this command-line is specific...to sp
dot net five we do want to have a similar command-line and other project types as well but if
...working in like a consul lap...informs app you would still use the package manager...and the.
I should also clarify this is like an alternative to the package
manage consult it doesn't actually work in sp...five at the moment but we do plan to
...that up by the time we ship so anyway let's start
using a migrations command so you probably notice the
...unicode come up to dimension unicorns a precious to us so in
...migration we'll call the migration last updated you remember too that I have
to context so I need to let f no which context I want to generate the migration for
...with...still context.
So, it's going to look at my model...going to look at what the model look like last time I
scaffold and migration and create the changes in
immigration for me so let's go to the migration photo we'll see what scaffold.
That's pretty good to me it's just going to add a column code last updated that is of type...to
...non-null sounds great.
We want to apply that to the database.
Some...run a similar command but instead of migration ad will say migration apply.
Okay, so, when this finishes we now have the last updated property
...model as shadow state we have a last updated column
in our database...not actually using it anywhere now code?
So, let's go back to the context of what I want to do is automatically set that property when
save changes call so I...out some code here
...the tech changes so detect changes are going to look for stuff that has changed my
...classes since the last time db context check for changes.
Normally this runs automatically as part of save changes but I actually want to run my logic before I
...by save changes I need to call it explicitly.
And, then get a final the change tracking entries for
...items and I'm interested in the ones where the
entry that added or modified.
...allude through those and we'll say entry.
For access one of the properties.
This could be a property that's a shatter property or it could be a property that's part of my
clr class and I can set the current value.
...looking for a new shoot so by this one.
Gets added to my car all right let's just dropped out to add database log.
Zooming for your again.
Right so here's the inset command so we can see that last updated is just included along with inset
commandos if it was any other property in my model and you can also see when we select
...also selecting the last updated column again the same as if it was just a property my
All right so you in a minute we're actually going to need some...database so...here let's just finish this order off.
I want that can ship it to me here that's not my real address stein's and...as a.
Place my what.
...at another order quickly...here.
My wife and I both love coffee
...set of matching unicode...for us because way that cool.
Ship...to the same address.
...us now we have a couple of what is in the database to.
All right so hopefully those few demo is gave the idea that you have seven has some
coney features coming...to...spending the whole time rewriting the core actually adding you stuff...seven as well
...switch gears a bit now and talk about the other part of the tag line the while.
One of my...tag line which was the new platforms
...so to a couple demos
...about you platforms so in the context of unicorns store.
They have a...responsible for.
Getting...the...come in packing them into boxes
putting ship a label on them and then shipping them out to customers hopefully in a timely manner the problem is that the moment
...a paper-based system lots of mistakes get made and it's not very efficient so we want to write
...application to help with that now warehouse is a
window shop we have windows desktops we have a few tablets around and we
give a lot of our employees windows find to use so we want to write
...application is useable across platforms so of course what we want to do is
write...ten universal application platform.
I've already might start on the application.
So, the first thing I'm going to do well
...before we start on it let's just talk about how this applications going to work the application is going
to talk to a central web api service.
It's going to ask that web api for all of the current orders that need to be
...shipped out the customers.
When it does that is going to...screen in the warehouse...I can go through...the...to fail and assign them to
...it...talk back to the service...in the central database
...these orders are currently being packed that point so that no other employee
tries to pack them as well now that point we want to take a copy of the order information and store it
locally on the desktop the tablet all the fine whatever we happen to be working on because
I warehouse is a big building...so full of metal and a whole bunch of other stuff and as dead spots
...so network a wi-fi or whatever so we need to be able to work offline...the orders?
And, then once the order has been shipped at some point we need to record
...the central service when we're online that the...has been shipped.
So, the communication with that web api services done through this unicorns store service
...thing that I've implemented here so we have a few things here we can get the pending orders which will give us back
a list of orders you say I'm just hitting has simple web api
and point here.
We can record the fact that I'm packing orders again just
hitting a different part of the web api and then I can also talk back to the
service and record when I've shipped in order moment this services just running on my local machine because
on developing at...it's here hosted on localized.
All right and the if we go look at the model I have here you see I have some simple
...classes that are return from the service I have this order and I
haven't order line as well now what I want to do is when I get that information back want to be a
distort somewhere locally on the device now obviously the default database of choice
when I'm talking about devices is sql...so let's go out and you get package we're going
to install entity framework dot sequel light so this is a sql lack provide of entity framework.
And, then I've got...start of a context you...got notice context inherits
...has a db set for the orders or lines I'm just reusing the same dt
...that were return from the service.
And, now that I have...light installed I can just go ahead and say options.
You...what you...and extension method that's now available because I have the sequel
...provider installed now I need to provide a connection string.
And, I've already got a bit of code on the line above that will find...appropriate filename to use.
Now the choose orders form is a section of the application where the users can choose the
...that I want to work on so it's mostly implemented but all I need to do is taken offline
copy of the data once...selected the orders so I knew that my context.
I'm liping through the orders I'm
going-to go ahead and on the orders db set adage...that.
Also interested in the order line information...each of the...lines.
...and then once I've added all of that I'm going to go ahead and call save changes to
flush those changes out to the database.
All right let's run it and see what happens.
you notice to start with I've got the target set to the local machine so this is going to be the desktop version of the application.
I can click on choose...it talks to the service I
get the orders back and say I want to fill that one.
Is going to tell me that the autos assigned to me?
And, then walking around the warehouse this one's an easy one so I say...the
Right...shipping label stick it on and then record the fact that I've ship the package.
All right if we go look at website.
And, my account I can go look at my orders.
And, we'll see that indeed the first-order there.
Is now...to shift?
And, of course because this is a universal application.
I can switch my target too.
Go ahead and run the application deployed off to the find emulator.
...one order there are many I'm going to select that one...it to me now the nice thing about the find emulator
as I can actually simulate offline so let's go take the emulate offline.
Just...than offline outcry and request the orders again.
...here it's telling me that could not connect...offline account talk
to local hosts machine but we can still go through and...the order so
plot the order we're going to...the think mug write the label and ship it.
...see I get a notification telling me that I'm not to the
...locally but I couldn't think that with the central service so I could do that later.
So, let's just bring the emulated back online.
we...the...button and...orders...now...recording the central database.
And,...describe refresh this page.
And, again, we'll see that by that what is...ship now so we're using entity framework with sequel
wyatt
on the phone desktop and tablet to take care of storing local data.
Let's keep going with the new platforms one.
So, there's another part of our business.
At unicorns store and that's a graphic design department now they have this really old system that
...use for tracking work
order so when someone in the unicorns store organization once and you piece like a
...ad for the website or something like...graphic design department I go into the work order
into this system and the designers can take...against that work order is like...
Now the graphic design department doesn't use windows they're running on os
So, as you might expect the original application was developed using os x.
Now we want to write dot net because where dot net development shop but,
the idea of going putting a windows machine on the desk just run this application
doesn't really appeal to the graphic design as it also doesn't appeal to the cfo of
...so we're going to use dot net on amac now you also might expect
...existing application has
an existing database not existing database is probably not going to be sequel
server if I'm talking about a microsystems so it's actually price...
so I will look here I have progressed instance that has a very simple schema
a little how to...on-screen...we have work orders and
...of courses has existing data in it because it's an existing application I can't just go
on move this database to a sequel server because we're going to do
and incremental roll-out of the new application so we need to have the existing are
...application talking to the existing database and down you want talking as well.
So, this point I want to start writing dot net code on amac using ef to talk to this
...chris database now the tool I choose here
is not important the point of this demo is that I can use any framework
anywhere that I write dot net code I could use visual studio code could be and targeting dot net
core for me I've actually chosen to use mono develop I'm going to write a
...front-end that uses the f to talk to that postscript database.
...the mono develop...which is now...
you'll see that I've made some progress on this application now obviously need to
...to talk to high-stress so the guys from the mpg sequel project
have very...work with this on a very short time frame to build-out or to
pull the mpg sequel provider across the...seven...now this isn't a demo
you-can tried home because you notice if...look at my packages.
A program...to say that on-screen...packages I don't have the entity framework dot mpg
sequel package installed what I actually have some binary is that the guys on the project
...provided to me that a link directly into my applications so the package will be coming
...for the moment just treat this is a preview of what you will be able to do...
All right so I've got some polka classes here I've got a note I have a work
...class and I've got the start of a context.
...this code by now the only thing I have to do is wire up the context
...my database.
So, obviously I'm using mpg...provide us so I can do build.
...this is an extension method I have
because I have that provider installed I already have my connection string stabbed out there.
So, now
...context is hooked up to our postscript database let's just go.
Look, at some of the code we have in the controller for the main window.
I guess I should point out at the top I'm creating an instance of the context it's going to live for the duration of the
window.
Here I'm using a link query to pullback
...orders for the user that's currently logged in...is going to be jeff that's login.
When they...a selects...jeff selects a particular work order
when...go ahead and use another link query to load the notes flat worker from the database?
then when the user tries to add another note when they do at another note will create an instance of the note
class who added to the notes db set and then go ahead and push that out to the database?
So, we see the...coming up on the screen one of the work...here.
Is an...una...
Will say there's a few nights here jeff discussing with
...suggested that we should just still the...coin that...jeff thinks that's a stupid idea?
And, then just to...actually working let's go back...quest database.
Will look at the notes?
And, we'll see that new comment that I just...written out to the postscript sequel database.
Yeah, you got samoa.
Just give me a second I'm going to do something to get...demo.
Taking over while I talk.
How many people in the room have seen the unicode click a demo that I've done before
for af seven?
...okay you've been missing out
unique unicode click is this very cool application that unicorns store does because
...constable wants to cash in on this whole craze of having?
Very simple not very sophisticated games on...in that
...occupy quite a lot about time what they want to do is have this picture vienna...flashes up and you click
as many times as you can in the a lot of time and it keeps track of your scores and it sounds really lame
...people are going to spend hours when they should be sleeping...picture the unicode
...and of course when you open the app is going to have some not
so subtle advertising that says hey like unicorns you should come to our website and check it out.
Now...department wants to run all platforms so they have
...heard about this cool product called salmon studio and
...phones which.
Should allow us to do just that that's not the one I...this one?
All right so here is...informs application I'm going to stick on our sex for the moment.
Just because that seems like the cool thing to do.
So, I've got unicode click here I have a model I have a game class
that's.
A simple game have a context.
And, then if I go look at the implementation the game pages where actually click the picture of the pretty
unique on.
So, if I look through this and...when the game finishes.
We create...instance of the game object we added to the db
sedona context and we call save changes.
And, then we have a school history page here.
So, I light up the games I want to get the ones with the highest scores
...to take up to the top five of them and then I go and...to...
It's kind of fire up in.
...you why with...not so subtle advertising to visit the unicorns store.
Will click play we have five seconds to...the unicorns many times as we can twenty-five is
...code twenty-five was my...school.
And, of course we can go to the...page in...the data coming back ...entity framework
sites entity framework running on ios in a dot net app written with them
Cool all right let's come back online with this guy.
So, we've got a few minutes left I just want to wrap up by showing you some resources that you can head
to if you want to learn more about...seven so let's actually
...and I'll show you some of them...
We'll look back over to my desktop...so entity framework
seventies opensource any framework is opensource in six as well used to be on
...lex the of seventies now and get hub now we're not just open sources and you can look
at source code but where properly opensource how issue track is public if you
go out wiki one of the interesting things you'll see here is we actually have design meeting nights?
Now we've had a bit of a period where we've been pretty light on the design meetings I guess we had one here
recently.
When we have design meetings we take notes and we published
...for people to give feedback on so
we're kind of inviting you into the development cycle before we even get to writing any code so,
here we're talking about layout of code when we do reverse engineering from existing database?
At this stage this is also the place you want to go to for
getting started information on have seven so you want to get started using the
...seven in a traditional dot application you would come here and tell you what
release you should use and how to get started and all those things too?
Should also mention way open-source and we do except contributions obviously we have a
fairly stringent process for code reviews and we expect you to write unit test and everything too so we're not just
accept any change that people want to give us what we are
open-source we do except contributions into the product and we have had a few great contributions from the community?
If you're not quite so interested in getting involved at that level but you want
...I more about aef seven than this link is on the slide but it's
...dot microsoft slash about aef seven.
...that one.
Which...to a page?
We have a link to have seven is but then also a series of blog
posts and other information we've done what you can dig into the new features that are coming
...seven and changes to the core analyze types of things there.
Don't worry about remembering all these urls are in the powerpoint for the dec
The other thing that you might be interested in is the demos I show looking at the code actually use to do
than so.
...minded have account.
Zooming for your again so you can see roughly
...again links in the decks that are about eating at the dec online afterwards
but my get have account has the unicorns still code on
it and you'll see here I have the completed source from the demo we have
the source code for everything we looked at here online.
All right there's everything I just showed you link on the slide so actually wrapped up with a few minutes
...space about time to take a couple of questions if you have questions and...just a step up to
the mike and probably just time to take
to questions so if someone wants to jump up and ask a question please go ahead.
You can ask...repay, yeah.
Question was is doesn't make any sense to have an
...data...for entity framework seven.
Not short something we've actually talked about it is interesting because often with our data you're getting data from a
database using any framework anyway so...provide on top of it it's not something up team is probably going to
implement but it is something that somebody else I could say outside about team working on in the future.
Our question was...to support inheritance folks may have seen...now announcement
...up until now we've said things like inheritance is not supported we had a stage where
transactions once supported but they are now supported so yes inheritance is actually a work-in-progress
...current code base actually some of the api
...data in the beta for bits that are available online now but,
it's not wide...throughout the stack so inheritance is coming it's just not...quiet.
What we implementing at the moment is a subset of what was in fsix I'm not sure that we're
going to build everything that was there and fsix into the stack because one of the things we don't want to do
support although like insanely crazy mappings you could
...but certainly a lot of the patents you can do any of six will be
supported gone is their way to generate models and different projects is...what sorry
...way to generate models and different projects to make models of different if
...firsts yep and if...generate the models
...right...yet so can ef make models for you projects
in different projects so do you want to classes spread throughout different projects...just one of
...for example, if...them and...the attributes yep whatever...them...windows
phone windows...I...use the attributes ride so you could put your
model your model can be in a different assembly if that's what you're asking...different projects you can do
...portable class library that has your project in it your model in it you could also across
...want to have attributes and you could put attributes and put some
compiler logic around them to strip them out what I would recommend doing that if you want to
have your model available on a platform that doesn't support attributes is just to you configuration using the
...api because that is available everywhere yep?
In app database first approach in the entity framework serving
...and will be will support abuse?
Question is will database
...generating from existing database support views in...seven.
It doesn't at the moment it would be extremely easy...in we're still.
We're still playing around the process at the moment it's just a
command line process and it's kind of an all-or-nothing thing you point of the database that generates for your
tables we're going to buildyou wireless kind of like what you're used to
...six-point-one...you can like pointed existing database pick the views and tables you
want I can't see any reason we would not include views in that dialogue and the ability to select
them...to take one more question, yeah.
You can select the view
the each has some problems that detecting the primary key
...so the question was it has when you selective view at the moment
in reverse engineer we generally just make every property in the view the primary
...we...be doing that when we do reverse engineering
...seven happen the reverse engineer processes completely new thing and we'll do something sensible
...seven that fsix is great but.
All right I mean the thank you very much free time I'm going to ask you to.
Filling out session evaluations is extremely useful to us it helps us get better
it's because so please take the time to fill went out for this and the other session to attend thanks.